Once upon a time, the dollar was as good as gold.
曾几何时，美元就如同黄金一样。
The United States and most other countries minted gold coins.
美国和其他各个国家铸造了一块块金币，
Paper money was a promise to pay in gold.
当时各国承诺可以纸币来兑换黄金。
But today, the dollar and most other world currencies
但是今天，美元和其他大多数货币，
are supported not by gold, but by credit
已经不再以黄金背书的货币，而转变为了信用货币，
paper backed by paper.
也就是没有抵押物单凭信用的纸币。
The experience of Germany in the early 1920s
在1920年代初的德国，
is the classic horror story
有一段经典的历史教训，
told by those who urge a return to the gold standard
那些极力要求恢复金本位制的人们认为，
as the best way to stop inflation and stabilize economies.
金本位是阻止通胀和稳定经济的最佳方法。
As prices rose, the government printed more and more currency
随着物价上涨，政府印制了越来越多的货币，
and prices soared again.
然后物价继续飙升。
Eventually, the German Mark literally was not worth
最终，德国马克不夸张地说，
the paper it was printed on.
甚至不如印钞所需纸张值钱。
Bundles of paper money were needed to buy a loaf of bread,
购买面包需要大量的纸币，
and a postage stamp cost millions.
甚至连一张邮票都要花费数百万。
What is the situation for scarcity? Why do we even need cryptocurrency?
什么是稀缺性呢？为什么我们需要加密货币？
Let's look at the everyday money that we use.
看看我们每天使用的金钱。
There's the US dollar,
有美元，
the Chinese yuan,
人民币，
the Euro and the Swiss franc.
欧元和瑞士法郎。
And what I'm showing here is
这里所展示的数据，
official government statistics as to
是有关的官方政府统计数据，
the amount of money in circulation.
纵轴是货币的流通量。
This is M1, which is
也就是 M1
paper money, currency
纸币，现金货币
and also checking accounts and savings accounts.
还有支票账户和活期储蓄帐户。
It's cash and things that act like cash
现金，或其作用类似于现金。
all together,
全部汇总在一起，
and each of these plots is showing
这些图的横坐标呢，
since October 2008, which is when the Bitcoin white paper came out.
是自2008年10月以来，也就是比特币白皮书发布的时间点开始。
That is the left-hand scale of each of these four plots.
这是四个图的左侧标度。
This is 2008 and then this is the end of 2019.
从2008年，到2019年底。
You can see that the money supply has inflated
你会发现货币的供应量在增长，
for everybody
对每个人来说，
In just 11 years
在短短的11年中，
the money supply of the US dollar has gone up 2.6 times.
美元的货币供应量增长了2.6倍。
In other words,
换句话说，
the printing presses of money have been going on at that rate.
印钞机永不停。
We don't really notice it because
我们没有意识到是因为，
every year the prices that we see go up a little bit
虽然每年我们都能感受到物价上涨了一丢丢，
but it's like the frog in boiling water, right?
但这个过程就好像温水煮青蛙，对吗？
The frog doesn't understand that
青蛙好像不明白，
it's sitting in boiling water until it's too late
青蛙在慢慢加热的温水中，等它意识到危险，为时已晚，
and it's cooked.
然后变成了熟蛙（可怜哇）。
That's the kind of
这个例子正像是，
situation that we find ourselves in.
我们目前所陷入的状况。
The thing is that
事实上，
all of the global Fiat currencies are kind of
所有全球法币，
turning on the printing presses at a disturbing rate.
都在以令人不安的速度打印着钞票。
But what counts as victory?
所以怎么才能不被通胀侵害？
What counts as being sound and
怎么才能算保值成功？
prudent with your particular country's currency?
尤其是在你国家怎么才算抗通胀和守住财富
Well, it's inflating slightly less fast than the other guys, right?
好吧，通胀速度比其他人慢，对吧？
We still have this situation where
可这样的情况呢，
if you zoom out,
具体来看这里，
for example, for the US dollar
例如，这个图表里，对于美元
you go to like a 50-year time scale
在50年的时间内，
you see basically an exponential growth curve.
显然看到了货币总量的指数增长曲线。
This is a problem that all savers face
这是所有储户都面临的问题，
anyone who has assets to save
任何要储存资产的人，
is up against this current that's coming up against them
都要面对法币增发，
in that they're constantly being diluted
因为它们的货币价值不断被稀释，
by new money that's being created.
以创造的新货币的方式。
2008 is when the Nakamoto white paper came out.
中本白皮书于2008年发布。
This is the Bitcoin white paper
这是比特币白皮书，
and the key insight to this
对于白皮书的关键概念，
I won't go too much into the
我不想说太多关于
geeky details, although
密码极客的技术细节，
I'm assuming that everyone here has an IQ of at least 140.
因为我估计在这里的听众（36c3黑客大会）的智商至少为140。
It wouldn't take you long
看比特币白皮书不会花你很长时间
if you haven't already,，
即使你还没有
to look at this paper and study it.
看过这篇论文并进行研究。
But I would say that
所以我想跳过那部分说的是，
the Nobel Prize in Economics can not be given to an anonymous person.
诺贝尔经济学奖不能授予匿名人士。
But were Satoshi Nakamoto (a) real person
中本聪是真实的人吗？
this clearly would be a
显而易见的是如果他是自然人
Nobel prize-winning insight in economics
应该是诺贝尔经济学奖得主。
in which
在那些
economics is just the study of scarcity, really.
真正对经济学中稀缺性的研究里。
What Nakamoto consensus does
中本聪共识是什么呢？
is it synthesizes a method
它综合了一系列方法，
to create digital scarcity
来创造数字稀缺性，
without needing a central authority
不需要中央权威
to maintain that scarcity.
来保持这种稀缺性（就好像黄金一样不能被凭空制造）。
In all of our national monies
在我们所有的国家货币体系中，
in the European Central Bank,
欧洲中央银行，
the Federal Reserve in America
美国联邦储备局，
these are all centrally governed bodies
这些都是中央治理的机构，
that decide what to do with the money supply.
他们来决定货币供应。
Now
目前，
the macroeconomic theory is that
在宏观经济理论中，
the money supply will expand and contract
货币供应量的扩大或收缩，
to match the actual economic output of the society.
会以匹配社会的实际经济产出为目的。
In other words, if a society is really productive and it makes a lot of stuff,
换句话说，如果一个社会真的富有生产力，并且它创造了很多东西，
then the society is justified in inflating the money supply because they've been productive.
那么就有理由增大货币供应量，因为它们希望印钞和生产创造的速度保持一致。
But the problem is that
但是问题是这样，
countries get into trouble.
各个国家陷入了困境。
They get into debt.
他们陷入了债务危机。
They promise services to people
他们曾承诺为人民服务，
that are too expensive and then they can't pay for them.
但又无力兑现诺言，
They go into debt.
因为负债累累。
The problem is that
另一个问题是，
mismanagement causes this kind of fragile balance
管理不善会影响货币供应量和基础经济规模之间脆弱的平衡，
between the size of the money supply and the size of the underlying economy,
to get out of whack.
为了让我们摆脱困境，
Why is it interesting to have
一个有趣的探索是，
a source of scarcity that doesn't require
创造一种稀缺资源，它不需要
a central committee to be making decisions
一个中央决策委员会来进行决策，
for that money
这个东西就是真正意义上的钱
Is that it offers
它将提供
a way for people to opt out
另一种货币和价值体系方式
of the Fiat monetary system.
也就是国家法币体系之外的东西。
It also provides a
它也化身为一个
kind of a fire under the feet of the
强大的竞争对手
Fiat central banks to be maybe do a little bit of a better job.
促使各国中央银行做得更好。
Maybe we
也许我们，
might have
可能会，
fewer financial crises in the future
减少未来金融危机的发生
Maybe we won't have another
也许我们不会再经历另一个
2009 style financial crisis.
2009年类似的金融危机。
The way that the Nakamoto consensus does this
中本聪共识的实现方式
there are three ways.
有三种方式。
At the account level
对于帐户层，
in other words,
举个例子，
how is it that one person's Bitcoin is not
怎么确定比特币归属于哪个人
confused with another person's Bitcoin?
不至于与另一个人的比特币混淆？
It's that
是这样子，
when a person signs up for a Bitcoin account, so to speak,
当一个人注册一个比特币帐户时，
what they're really doing is picking a number.
他们真正在做的是选一个号码
They're just picking a number out of a
他们只是从一堆号码中挑选一个号码
256-bit field.
256位字段。
People are really bad at
人们真的很不擅长，
imagining huge numbers
想象大量的数字，
but we're talking about picking a number between 0 and 10 to the 77th.
但我们谈论的是取一个0到10之间的数字的10^77。
One with 77 zeroes after that.
在那之后有77个0。（10000000000000000000000000000000.... 77个0）
To understand how big that is，
要了解它有多大，
imagine the diameter of the Milky Way galaxy.
想象一下银河系的直径。
Now imagine electrons
再想象下电子，
being lined up
电子在银河系中排队，
right next to each other
彼此相邻，
and I'm using just the classical electron radius here.
我在这里只使用经典的电子半径
For the entire diameter of the Milky Way we have electrons lined up.
对于银河系的整个直径，我们都有电子排列。
That turns out to not be enough.
事实上这还不够，
You have to take one of these electrons
你需要把这些电子，
and blow that up to the size of the Milky Way galaxy
吹至银河系的大小
and then get another set of electrons going across.
然后得到一组排队的电子（多个银河系叠加）
even that's not enough,
那还不够，
you have to take one of those electrons,
你必须再把这些电子
blow it up to the size of this hall
吹到这个大厅那么大
and then you have bacteria lined up one after each other.
然后把它们叠加排成一列。
That's 10 to the 77th.
那就是10^77。
That's how vast the space is of the random number that you're choosing
这就是您选择的随机数的空间有多大，
and that is why getting a Bitcoin account doesn't require
这就是为什么比特币帐户不需要
going to fill out some form and asking permission for an account.
将要填写一些表格并要求获得帐户许可。
You just pick a number.
您只需选择一个数字（和别人撞到同一个account的概率非常非常非常小）。
You just pick a number,
你只要选一个号码
that's your private key and you need to
那就是你的私钥，
kind of defend that
你需要保护它，
because knowledge of that private key
因为知道那个私钥，
is what is needed to spend a person's Bitcoin.
就可以花费这个私钥解锁的比特币。
The aggregate level of scarcity, that is,
从稀缺程度上来说，
how do we know how much of the Bitcoin there is in the entire monetary system?
我们如何知道整个货币系统中有多少比特币？
and how do we know that's not going to get corrupted?
我们怎么知道不会被破坏（增发/丢失）？
Well, the scarcity is
好吧，稀缺性是由，
enforced by an open network of miners
开放的矿工网络来保证，
which are really gossipy accountants
真正的会计师，
and they are rewarded for behaving consistently with the consensus rule set.
并且他们因遵守一致规则集而获得奖励。
Finally, how do we know that the record of
最后，我们如何知道
who sent what to who
谁向谁发送了什么？
which is, what the blockchain records.
这就是根据区块链所记录的内容，
The blockchain is a series of blocks.
区块链是一系列的块组成的链式数据结构。
Each block contains transactions from
每个区块包含了多笔交易
this person sent money to this person.
交易记录了某个人发送钱到另一个人，
Who sent what to who and how much
谁向谁发送了什么以及发送了多少，
and each block is just a record of that.
每个区块都包含一系列记录。
How do we know that that's not going to get corrupted over time?
我们怎么知道那不会随着时间的流逝而恶化？
Because, as we all know, there's bit rot.
因为，腐败。
There can be corruption,
可能会有腐败，
there could be some
可能有一些，
malfeasance going on with the state of the database.
数据库状态持续不正常。
The database is maintained because each block
区块链数据库由多个块构成，
has a small data field in it that the miner can change
里面有一个小的数据字段，矿工可以更改，
that's called the nonce.
那就是随机数。
And each miner，
每个矿工，
randomly changes the nonce so that the hash of the block is lower than a number,
随机更改随机数，以使块的哈希值小于这个数字，
called the difficulty.
叫做难度。
Usually when we talk about hash functions
通常当我们谈论哈希函数时，
we don't care about the actual value of the hash function.
我们不在乎哈希函数的实际值。
We just care that the hash matches some other hash.
我们只关心哈希与其他哈希是否匹配。
Like if you're checking for file integrity,
就像你要检查文件的完整性一样，
then you would take the hash of the file that you downloaded
那么你将对下载文件进行hash
and compare that with the hash of the file that you're looking for
然后将其与您要查找的文件的哈希值进行比较
and you compare those.
然后比较一下。
In this case, we're actually caring about the number of the hash.
在这种情况下，我们实际上关心的是哈希数。
How small, how large is that number
这个数字有多小，多大
and the difficulty is a number that must be
而困难则是一个数使得
satisfied by each block.
每个块都适合。
In other words,
换一种说法，
the hash of each block needs to be lower than the difficulty.
每个区块的哈希值必须低于难度。
To make a real world analogy of this,
为了真实地类比，
imagine that you have (an) accounting book
想象你有一本会计帐簿
and each page of the accounting book has 10 minutes worth of transactions on it.
并且会计帐簿的每一页上都有10分钟的交易时间。
You want to make a way to make sure that
你想要一种方法来确保
each page is really rare in some way.
每个页面在某种程度上确实很稀有。
One way you could do this is you could say
你可以这样
the mass of every page of this accounting book has to be an even multiple of 1 million atoms.
该会计账簿每一页的质量必须是100万个原子的偶数倍。
Each accountant is going to be
每个会计师都将，
kind of touching the paper,
碰这个纸，
rubbing it, erasing little bits
擦，擦一点，
because at that level you're taking away or adding
因为在那个级别上，你可能减少了也可能增加了，
trillions and trillions of atoms
数万亿个原子，
so it's going to be a random number whether
所以擦纸后纸的质量将是一个随机数，
your page is actually a exact multiple of a million atoms.
您的纸实际上是一百万个原子的精确倍数，
Once that's found,
一旦找到，
that's a very rare page.
那是非常罕见的纸。
It's a rare page because it has an
这是一个罕见的纸，因为它有一个，
exact multiple of 1 million atoms to it
一百万个原子的精确倍数。
and because it's now a digital representation,
因为现在是数字表示，
you can copy that exactly.
你可以完全复制这个纸。
Now you have a chain of blocks,
现在您有了一堆块，
each one of these has this rare attribute
每一个块都具有这种罕见的属性
and the blockchain links them all together.
区块链将它们链接在一起。
Scarcity in Bitcoin and Monero
比特币和门罗币的稀缺性
they both have an original code base.
他们都有原始的代码库（门罗不是比特的分叉也不是其他的分叉）。
There are many, many projects in cryptocurrency in which
加密货币项目有很多很多，
Bitcoin was simply forked and modified a little bit,
很多只是简单地分叉比特币和修改了一点参数，
(but) that's not the case in Monero.
但是，门罗币的情况并非如此。
It was written from scratch.
它是从头开始写的。
The elliptic curves used are different;
使用的椭圆曲线是不同的。
this is a form of technical hedging.
这是技术对冲的一种形式。
In Bitcoin the secp256k1 elliptical curve is used
在比特币中，使用secp256k1椭圆曲线，
whereas in Monero it's ed25519.
而在Monero中则是ed25519。
Both Bitcoin and Monero, as I mentioned before, require a private key.
正如我之前提到的，比特币和门罗币都需要私钥。
Spending the cryptocurrency requires that you know a number
发送加密货币需要你知道一个数字，
and that's the private key.
那就是私钥。
That's true in both Bitcoin and Monero.
比特币和门罗币都是如此。
Where we start to differ is that
我们开始有所不同的是
Monero also has what's called a view key.
门罗币还具有所谓的查看私钥。
The view key is another private key
查看私钥是另一个私钥
which is actually as kind of a subset of the spend key.
实际上，查看私钥功能是发送私钥的子集。
The view key is what is needed to decrypt
查看密钥是用来解密的，
the transactions on the blockchain that you personally are involved with.
解密区块链上和你相关的交易。
If you have the view key
如果你有查看私钥，
you can see what transactions you were involved in on the blockchain.
你可以在区块链上看到您参与了哪些交易，
Everything else remains encrypted.
而其他人的内容均保持加密状态。
The address spaces is different,
地址空间也不同，
in Bitcoin it's 10 to the 60th, in Monero it's 10 to the 76th.
在比特币中是10^60，而在门罗币中是10^76。
There are more addresses available in Monero,
门罗币的地址更多（此外门罗还有子地址功能，可以每次使用不同的接收地址来提升隐私性），
which means if you're worried about the birthday problem
这意味着如果你担心 “生日问题”
the birthday problem is the problem in which
生日的问题是什么呢？
if you have a group of 30 people,
如果你有一个30人的团体，
chances are much higher than you would expect that 2 people out of those 30 have the same birthday.
2个人生日相同的几率要比30生日相同的几率高的多
If you extend this now to the problem of picking a random number
如果将其扩展到选择随机数作为账户的问题
and calling it your own for
并称这个账户是自己的
a cryptocurrency account, you have the same problem.
一个加密货币帐户，和生日问题是一样的。
There's no guarantee that
没有人能保证，
the random number that you picked for your cryptocurrency account
你生成的私钥不会被别人生成，
is not going to subsequently be picked by me.
以及你生成的私钥不是别人的，
That's the birthday problem and
这就是生日的问题，
the birthday problem is less of a concern the more addresses there are.
地址越多相同私钥的可能性越小。
The emission deceleration is another difference between Bitcoin and Monero.
供应量减少的速度是比特币和门罗币之间的另一个区别，
In Bitcoin it's step-wise.
在比特币中，这是跳跃的，（大家一般称为减半）。
You might have heard of this thing called "the halvening".
您可能听说过这种叫做“减半”的事情。
This is: every 4 years, in Bitcoin,
每四年，比特币，
the number of Bitcoins that gets rewarded to miners
奖励给矿工的比特币数量，
as a reward for finding a page in the blockchain gets cut in half.
都会比之前减少一半。
Which means that on every miners calendar
这意味着在每个矿工他的日历上，
there's a date circled in red that
有一个用红色圈起来的日期，
their income is going to get cut in half.
他们的挖矿收入将减少一半（可以理解为减薪，在付出同样工作量的情况下薪水减半，为了收入需要更加努力）。
And that introduces a bunch of
这其实引入了
needless drama, really, in mining.
不必要的东西。
In Monero, we avoid this by having a continuously decreasing emission.
在门罗币中，我们通过不断减少排放来避免这种情况，（可以理解为慢慢减少奖励，每一天都在缓慢减少）。
Now another difference is in
现在另一个区别是，
what is the emission rate of coins in the far future.
在不久的将来，币的增发率是多少？
In Bitcoin, the block reward eventually goes to zero
在比特币中，区块奖励最终变为零，
and they anticipate using transaction fees to make up the difference.
他们期望使用交易费用来弥补差额，（即用80比特币每日奖励来弥补1800比特币每日奖励，2020年4月数据）
In Monero, there we have a concern that we want to always be assured that
在门罗币，我们有顾虑所以要确保
miners will have incentive to keep working for the system.
矿工将有动力继续为该系统工作。
And (in) Monero we have what's called a tail emission
门罗将有尾部的供应，
which works out to be 0.6 Monero per block
每个区块0.6个门罗币的奖励，
that goes on in perpetuity.
永远持续下去。
But that future money basically gets used to pay miners
未来的钱用于向矿工支付，
to continue to provide security for the network.
继续为网络提供安全性。
What's the far future inflation rate then?
那么远期的通货膨胀率是多少？
In Bitcoin, they can say it's exactly zero.
在比特币中，可以说它完全为零，
In Bitcoin they're fond of saying there's only ever going to be 21 million Bitcoins created
系统只会创造2100万个比特币，
and that's an easy thing for people to understand.
这是人们容易理解的事情。
But in Monero, we have constant linear inflation
但是在门罗币中，有恒定的线性通货膨胀
but it's not really correct to say that this is "infinite supply" as
如果说这是“无限供应”，那么并不是真的正确，
that's what gets bandied about.
这是门罗被谣言中伤的日常
Because if you look at the inflation rate, in Monero,
因为如果你查看门罗的通货膨胀率，
it asymptotically goes to zero.
它渐近地趋于零。
If you look at any macroeconomic theory,
如果你看过任何宏观经济学理论，
what the relevant variable is
什么是相关变量？
is the inflation rate.
是通货膨胀率。
Nobody really cares that
没有人真的在乎，
the nominal amount of US dollars is going up by whatever trillions of dollars per year.
美元每年增发数万亿美元。
It's the percentage that matters
但重要的是百分比，
and in Monero that percentage is already low and
门罗币，这个增发率已经很低了（目前低于比特币和未来一段时间2040都要低于比特币）
it'll continue getting lower.
它会继续降低。
Some curves to show what I'm talking about
曲线显示了我在说什么
These are supply emission curves showing
这些是供应排放曲线，
how many coins of each type exist as a function of time.
每种类型存在多少币相对时间的函数。
You can see that Monero had a later start here
看到门罗币从这里开始
and it has a tail emission.
它有尾部供应。
This tail emission is this constant linear slope.
该尾部供应是线性的。
The reason for this slope, again, is that
线性的原因呢，
the new coins that get emitted are being rewarded to miners who helped secure the network.
是为了激励矿工能够长久的维持网络的运行和安全性。
Whereas in Bitcoin, they have an impending problem to deal with.
而在比特币中，有一个迫在眉睫的问题需要处理。
And that their coin emission is coming up to this 21 million mark,
发行到达2100万之后，
it's going to go basically to zero.
增发将为0。
Then there are some papers out there that have
有一些论文指出，
proposed that the security of the network might be in jeopardy at that point.
那时网络的安全性会遭到冲击。
What if we take the first derivative of this curve
如果我们采用该曲线的一阶导数
so, we look at how much more supply is there in this year versus last year.
因此，我们看今年与去年相比有多少供应。
In other words, what's the inflation rate?
换句话说，通货膨胀率是多少？
Here's what you see.
这就是你所看到的。
I'm comparing several different assets here.
我在这里比较几种不同的资产。
This is the inflation rate of gold.
这是黄金的通货膨胀率。
We usually don't think of gold is inflating
我们通常不认为黄金会膨胀，
but of course there are miners
但是，
there are actual physical miners digging in the ground and
当然有实际的矿工在地下挖矿，
coming up with gold chunks to add to the world's supply of above-ground gold.
挖出金块以增加世界上地上黄金的供应。
That turns out to be about 1.5% per year of inflation in gold.
事实证明，这相当于每年黄金通胀的1.5％。
So if you think of gold as being sound money
因此，如果你认为黄金是可靠的货币，
then that 1.5% inflation rate is going to be sort of a line in the sand.
那么1.5％的通货膨胀率简直是毛毛雨啦。
As you can see - both Bitcoin and Monero
如你所见，
this dotted blue line is showing where we are right now.
蓝点虚线显示了我们现在的位置。
We're coming to a very interesting point in cryptocurrency history
我们正在进入加密货币历史中非常有趣的点
in that, up until now
直到现在
there's been a lot of emission happening.
过去已经发行了很多，
In order to get these coins out there
在那里，
the block rewards have been relatively high
区块奖励相对较高，
but we're now coming up on a new kind of era of scarcity
但我们现在正进入一种新的稀缺时期，
if you look at this to the right of here.
看这里右边，
And in fact, the inflation rate of Monero is going to be lower than that of Bitcoin
实际上，门罗币的通货膨胀率将低于比特币
for the next 6 years, until 2025.
接下来的6年，直到2025年。
Then there's going to be a 4 year period when they're about the same
然后大约是4年之后，
and then, starting in 2029, the
从2029年开始，
inflation rate of Bitcoin will once again go below Monero.
比特币的通货膨胀率将再次低于门罗币。
But then, again, this comes at with a question mark:
但是，这又带有一个问号？
how are those miners going to be paid, to be incentivized to support the network?
那些矿工将如何获得报酬，以激励他们支持网络？
Since that is a crucial feature of Nakamoto consensus,
由于这是中本聪共识的重要特征，
that game theoretically, all of the miners are incentivized to be honest
从理论上讲，所有矿工都需要受到激励，
and not to try to game the system for their own greed.
而不是为了自己的贪婪而继续游戏系统。
There's a form of unwanted scarcity and that's mining hardware.
此外，有一种形式的不必要的稀缺，那就是挖矿硬件。
And this is something that has been a big issue in Monero.
在门罗中，这一直是一个大问题。
In the Bitcoin white paper, Nakamoto wrote "one CPU, one vote"
中本聪在比特币白皮书中写道：“一个CPU代表着一个投票权”
and that idea is that the reward that a miner gets
这是矿工获得的报酬的依据，也就是工作量证明
should be proportional to their effort.
奖励应该与他们的努力成正比。
It should be proportional to the expense
应该与费用成比例，
that the miner incurred in mining.
这是矿工在采矿中发生的。
In other words, there should ideally be a linear function
换句话说，理想情况下应该有一个线性函数，
between the miners expense and the miners reward.
在矿工费用和矿工报酬之间。
Now, unfortunately, economies of scale in silicon manufacturing
现在，不幸的是，集成电路制造的规模经济，
have destroyed this linear relationship.
破坏了这种线性关系，
In other words, if you have about 25 million dollars
换句话说，如果您有大约2500万美元
to spend on a new fabrication facility in Shenzhen,
花费在深圳的新制造工厂，
then you can turn out your own silicon chips that do nothing but
然后您可以制造自己的硅芯片，
do the Bitcoin proof-of-work.
没有其他用处但可以做比特币的工作量证明。
These are ASICS, and
这些芯片被称为 ASICS，（专门针对某种运算特别制作的芯片，没有其他用处，也不是先进科技）
they've been on the network, on Bitcoin for several years now,
他们已经在网络上挖了很多年比特币了，
to the point that at this point Bitcoin mining is basically a cns oligopoly.
至此，比特币的开采基本上就是中国的寡头垄断。
This brings up centralization concern.
这引起了人们对集中化的关心。
It's not necessarily a problem that it's cn that has all the mining.
挖矿集中化当然是个问题，
It's really more of a problem that
这实际上是一个更大的问题
it's one certain area of the world that has
这是世界上某个拥有
basically control of all of the world's Bitcoin hash power.
基本上控制着世界上所有的比特币哈希能力。
There are further news items that are cause for concern,
还有其他新闻值得关注，
for example, the growing trade war bewtween China and West.
例如，中国和西方世界愈演愈烈的贸易战。
There is a press article out that said
有一篇新闻是这样说的
the Chinese government has recently decreed that
中国政府最近颁布法令
only Chinese computer hardware is to be uesd in government offices
中国政府办公室里只能使用中国制造的电脑硬件
starting in like a year.
从新一年开始
There's some deadline by which of the dells and
在某个截至日期前美国戴尔公司和其它
American companies' computers are to be kicked out,
美国公司的计算机将被踢出其市场，
so something similar could well happen for manufactured Bitcoin ASICS.
因此，比特币ASICS矿机可能会发生类似的情况。
We kind of take for granted that there's a free flow of goods in the world
我们认为世界上货物自由流通是理所当然的
but what happens if not only does one part of the world control the manufacture
但是,如果只有一家工厂垄断了制造会怎样
of all of the crypto hash power
也就是所有的算力
but then is unable to even export it due to a trade war.
矿机甚至无法出口。
In Monero we tried to take this decentralization question quite seriously
门罗对待这个问题严肃审慎，
and we've done some changes to the proof-of-work
我们对工作量证明做了一些更改，
to support the little guy who's mining.
支持挖矿的小朋友们。
That is, when Bitcoin started
也就是说，当比特币开始时，
it was possible for just a regular person running
一个普通人挖比特币是可能的，
the Bitcoin client on their computer to actually have a shot
他们计算机上的比特币客户端实际上是有机会的，
at getting a mining reward.
去得到一些采矿奖励。
Those days are long gone because now
那些日子早已一去不复返了，因为现在，
the hash power is dominated by these massive farms of ASICS.
哈希率主要由ASICS的这些大型矿场掌握。
It's just hopeless for any little guy to try to mine Bitcoin.
任何小家伙都无法尝试开采比特币。
In Monero, we're trying to change that
门罗币正在尝试改变这一点，
and the proof of work has been modified several times.
并且工作量证明算法已多次修改。
Now, as of just last month,
现在，截至上个月，
the proof of work in Monero is now RandomX
Monero的工作量证明算法是 RandomX，
which actually uses every single capability of a CPU
实际上使用了CPU的所有指令集
in doing the proof of work.
在工作量证明的过程中，
There's a basically a random program that gets executed.
有一个随机程序可以执行。
Each core of the processor needs 2 gigabytes of RAM to run well.
处理器的每个核心需要2GB的RAM才能正常运行。
This was a design decision made to
这是个设计是为了
make it harder for botnets to control the network,
使僵尸网络更难以控制网络，（也就是少数黑客很难控制大量普通用户电脑进行对网络的控制）
because if your computer is infected with a botnet
因为如果您的计算机感染了僵尸网络，
and 14 out of your 16 gigabytes of RAM are being eaten up,
在16GB的RAM中消耗了14GB，
you're probably going to notice it.
你怎么会注意不到它。
It was deliberate that design decision in RandomX to use a
这是 RandomX 特意设计的，
high required amount of RAM for processing.
计算所需大量内存。
There's another source of scarcity
还有另一个稀缺性来源，
that is not necessarily one that you want in a blockchain,
不一定是您想要在区块链中使用的那个，
and that is access to layer one.
那就是通过第一曾网络，也就是主网。
Bitcoin's 1 megabyte block limit caused a project fork.
比特币的1兆字节的区块大小限制导致了项目分叉，（比特币社区分裂，目前三个币都声称自己是比特币）
There was basically a civil war in Bitcoin over whether or not it was okay
使得比特币还存在一场内战，
to make blocks stay at this 1 megabyte limit.
为了使块大小保持1MB的限制，
It still rages on to this day. It's still a holy war
这仍然是一场圣战。
and this is something that Monero has avoided thus far.
这是迄今为止Monero要避免的事情。
Its solution to this is to use a adaptive block size
它的解决方案是使用自适应块大小
in which the maximum block size of a Monero block is flexible
其中Monero块的最大块大小是灵活的，可以变大也可以变小
and it can organically expand or shrink along with demand.
可以随着交易需求进行有机扩展或缩小。
With, of course, provisions in there
当然，其中有一些规则，
to prevent the system from getting gamed.
以防止系统被攻击（例如某分山对比特币进行了碎片交易攻击）
And there's ongoing research to reduce the transaction size.
并且门罗研究院也在进行减小交易规模的研究。
There's bulletproofs that went in recently
比如最近的防弹协议，
that reduce transaction sizes by a factor of 10, that went in.
使得交易中所需空间减少了10倍，
And overnight the transaction fees for transacting Monero went down by a factor of 10
同时，Monero的交易费用下降了10倍，
because the transaction fee is based on the kilobyte size of the transaction.
因为交易费用基于交易的千字节大小。
This baby is just one second old.
这个婴儿刚刚降生，
Here in the delivery room
在纽约西奈山医院的
of Mount Sinai Hospital in New York,
分娩室
he has just won his first fight
赢得了第一场战斗
the fight to life.
为生命而战。
His parents allowed our cameras to film his birth.
他的父母允许我们的相机拍摄他的出生。
His footprints are taken for identification.
他的脚印被用于识别。
He is still less than a minute old, and this is his first record.
出生还不到一分钟，这是他的第一个记录。
His file has begun.
他的档案记录已经开始。
When this baby is a young man
当这个婴儿是年轻人时
celebrating his 17th birthday,
庆祝他的17岁生日，
the year will be 1984.
那将是1984年。
Will his 1984 be the world that George Orwell foresaw
他的1984年会成为乔治·奥威尔（George Orwell）预见的世界吗？
a world stripped of privacy,
一个剥夺隐私的世界，
a world watched by Big Brother?
老大哥总是看着你的世界？
Or will this child have what Justice Brandeis
还是这个孩子有布兰代斯大法官
at the turn of the century labeled
在世纪之交声明的
our inalienable right,
我们不可剥夺的权利
the right to enjoy life,
享有生活的权利，
the right to privacy?
隐私权？
Bitcoin is transparent.
比特币是透明的。
If you are new to crypto you might be under the impression
如果你不熟悉加密货币，或者外行，那么你可能会以为
that if you have Bitcoin you're anonymous.
如果你拥有比特币，那你就是匿名的。
It's this "anonymous magic internet money"
以为比特币就是神奇的互联网匿名币
that you might have heard about.
就像你可能曾经听说过的。
Nothing could be further from the truth
但是这跟事实相差甚远
the popular press continues to push this misleading narrative.
大众媒体继续推动这种误导性的叙述。
Bitcoin is completely transparent
事实上比特币是完全透明的，
and if you read the Bitcoin white paper, it's all there.
如果您阅读了比特币白皮书，就应该明白了。
It's specified that the sender, the receiver and how much got sent
发送者，接收者以及发送了多少，全部都公开和透明，
is recorded in plaintext and recorded in the blockchain.
以明文记录保存在区块链中，（不可更改，也删不掉）
Which, because it has all this proof-of-work up behind it --
这是它背后拥有的工作量证明决定的。
remember what I was saying about each transaction in the block
还记得我刚才怎么描述区块中的每个交易？
has a hash that makes it a very rare and unique set of data,
哈希值使其成为非常稀有且唯一的数据，
it's the multiple of 1 million atoms thing, right --
是一百万个原子的倍数，
basically, these transparent details are written and etched into that blockchain forever.
基本上，这些透明的细节将永远写入并蚀刻到该区块链中。
There is no escaping that
都是细节。
it's completely incompatible, for example, with European privacy law, the GDPR.
它与欧洲隐私法GDPR完全不兼容。
Which has this "right to be forgotten"
哪里拥有“被遗忘的权利”
that is totally non-existent in Bitcoin.
在比特币中完全不存在。
Once a transaction gets put into the Bitcoin blockchain it's there.
一旦交易进入比特币区块链，它就在那里。
It's there forever.
它永远存在。
And the only thing that is not
唯一不是完全透明的是
totally transparent is that the Bitcoin address
比特币地址
is just a hex string - it's a string.
只是一个十六进制字符串-这是一个字符串。
I mean,
我的意思是，
when you come down to it, everything's a hex string
当您使用它时，一切都是十六进制字符串
but the Bitcoin address is a sequence of letters and numbers that looks anonymous.
但是比特币地址是一个字母和数字的序列，看起来似乎是匿名的。
But once that gets associated to your name and face,
但是一旦地址与您的名字和面孔相关联，
that association, that metadata,
所有相关的数据，元数据，
that marriage between a Bitcoin account number and your identity,
比特币帐号和你的身份之间的绑定，
that doesn't change
不会改变
because the blockchain is etched in stone forever.
因为区块链永远固若金汤。
And it's constantly growing.
而且它还在不断增长。
The job of the people trying to identify and "dox" everyone
有些人们的工作就是试图识别和“人肉搜索”所有人
is - it's just a waiting game.
这是一场伺机而动的伏击。
You have this blockchain every day.
通过个区块链。
You get some little piece of information:
您会获得一些信息：
"Oh, you know, Joe in Leipzig signed up with (an) exchange".
“哦，您知道，乔在莱比锡与（一家）交易所签约了”。
Now their identity information is associated with this.
现在，他们的身份信息与此相关联。
Basically, this metadata just kind of
基本上，这种元数据只是
continues to gather on this blockchain until you have a situation
继续聚集在这个区块链上，直到遇到情况
which is actually much worse than in Fiat.
这实际上比法币差得多。
When you have a Fiat bank account you do not expect that your bank is going to post your monthly statement
当您拥有法币银行帐户时，不要指望银行将发布您的月结单
up on the bulletin board outside the bank for everybody to see.
放在银行外的公告板上，以供所有人查看。
But that is exactly the situation in Bitcoin
但这正是比特币的情况，
and it's not just the people out in your neighborhood who can see it.
不仅可以看到您附近的人，
It's everybody. Everybody in the world can see
还有这个系统上世界上的所有人，
who sent what to who and when.
谁向谁以及何时发送了什么。
The unfortunate consequence of this, is that
不幸的结果是
Bitcoins have a history behind them.
每个比特币背后都有一段历史。
Remember that in Bitcoin, every Bitcoin in existence
请记住，在比特币中，每个比特币都存在
first came into being as a reward that went to a miner.
最初是作为奖励给予矿工的。
Once the miner gets that Bitcoin and then they spend it, it starts circulating in the Bitcoin economy.
一旦矿工获得了比特币，然后他们花了它，它就会开始在比特币经济中流通。
But because the blockchain is transparent, it's totally "see-through".
但是因为区块链是透明的，所以它完全是“透明的”。
The entire history of every single Bitcoin now in existence can be traced back
可以追溯到现存的每个比特币的整个历史
to this person all the way back to when it was mined.
一直追溯到该人被开采时。
It's as if you have a 10 euro banknote
就好像您有一张10欧元的钞票
and on the back of that 10 euro banknote you see a nice list showing
在那张10欧元的钞票背面，您会看到一个漂亮的清单，显示
everyone before you who owned that.
从它发行到流通到你手里，曾拥有它的每个人的名字。
What could possibly be the negative consequences of this?
这可能带来什么负面后果？
How about innocent people getting falsely accused
例如无辜的人被错误指控
because they happen to have received money from somebody who unbeknownst to them
因为他们碰巧是从一个陌生人那里收到的钱
was involved in something that was not very good.
卷入了不好的事情。
This is happening in Bitcoin.
这在比特币生态中正在发生。
There's a reputation in Bitcoin that transfers as well as value
比特币有一种声誉，既可以转移价值
and that is what is profoundly disturbing about having this.
这就是对此的深深困扰。
And I call it a surveillance coin.
我称比特币为监视币。
In a surveillance coin, it's not just value that transmits
用监视币来说，传递的不仅仅是数值，
it's also reputation. Which means
还有声誉，
if you're accepting money from somebody,
如果您接受别人的钱，
you're also accepting their life history.
您也正在接受他们的历史。
It's coming to you too. It's not just value.
历史和你连接在一起，这不只是数值。
In contrast, Monero is fungible.
相反，门罗币是可互换的。
Fungible just means that every unit of currency is
可互换货币意味着每个货币单位都是1:1的
indistinguishable from the other units.
与其他单位没有区别。
If I have 10 Monero, you have 10 Monero and then
如果我有10个门罗币，那么你有10个门罗币
we both trade the 10 Monero to other people, they still look like the 10 Monero.
我们都将10Monero交易给其他人，他们看起来仍然像10Monero。
There's no history. It works just like a cash bill.
没有历史，就像现金一样。
It works just you think cash should work.
就像现金一样。
And it does this by adding three technologies
就像现金一样，它通过添加三种技术来做到这一点，
on top of what Bitcoin does that preserve privacy.
提供了比特币没有的隐私的功能。
One is ring signatures.
首先是环签名。
In ring signatures,
在环签名中，
the sender of funds is lined up along with 10 other senders of funds
资金发送者与其他10个资金发送者混在一起
and the only thing that you know happened in that transaction is one out of those 11 people sent money.
而且您知道该交易中发生的唯一一件事是，这11个人有一个人发送了钱。
It's as if every time you spend money,
好像每次花钱一样
now you have 10 friends or 10 random people, 10 decoys
现在您有10个朋友或10个随机人，10个诱饵
and all that you know, cryptographically, is one of the 11 have sent the money.
从密码上来说，您所知道的就是这11个汇款中的一个。
That protects the sender's identity.
这样可以保护发送者的身份。
How about the receivers identity?
其次接收者的身份如何？
Well, the receiver's Monero account does not appear unencrypted on the Monero blockchain.
接收者的门罗币帐户同样不是透明的。
A one-time-use address is what gets put on the blockchain
一次性地址是放在区块链上的内容
so that protects the recipients' privacy.
从而保护收件人的隐私。
How about the amount that gets sent? Because there are
最后汇出的金额如何保密？
attacks that can be done by knowing,
因为有些攻击者会根据金额进行攻击，
kind of observing your pattern of how much you spend.
观察您的支出方式。
That is covered with technology, RingCT,
技术涵盖了RingCT，
which originally was developed for Bitcoin but actually first got implemented in Monero.
它最初是为比特币开发的，但实际上在Monero中实现。（至今也没被比特币使用）
RingCT stands for confidential transactions.
RingCT代表机密交易。
And all these things (are) combined to make Monero's fungibility.
所有这些东西加在一起，使门罗币具有可互换性。
The end result is that in Monero,
最终结果是在Monero中，
coins are indistinguishable from their another or they have no memory.
硬币与另一个硬币没有区别，或者它们没有记忆。
They have no memory of where they've been,
他们不记得自己去过的地方
which is really what you want in a money because the opposite,
这确实是你想要的钱,
if you have money that has perfect memory, like it is in Bitcoin,
这确实是你想要的钱, 你难道更喜欢带记忆的钱吗，就像比特币这种
that unfortunately gets used to falsely associate activities of people who had nothing to do with each other.
总是不幸的错误地将彼此无关的人的活动与他人联系起来。
Because Monero is fungible, users benefit by having privacy.
由于门罗币是可互换的，因此用户可以从拥有隐私中受益。
The Monero blockchain is public just like Bitcoin.
Monero区块链就像比特币一样是公共的。
There is a publicly shared ledger
有一个公开共享的分类帐
of who sent what to who that everybody in the world can get.
可以像全世界任何人发送一笔钱，
All you have to do is download the Monero software and you too
您所要做的就是下载Monero软件
can have a copy of this ledger, of that has the complete history of who sent what to who.
然后拥有门罗区块链的副本，其中包含谁向谁发送了什么的完整历史记录。
The difference is that, in Monero,
区别在于，在门罗币中
the details of this blockchain are encrypted
该区块链的细节已被加密
so that if you just look at it, you see encrypted garbage.
这样一来，如果只看它，就会看到加密的垃圾。
You cannot do what you can do in Bitcoin which is
您不能做您可以在比特币中做的事情
type in somebody's Bitcoin address and immediately see how much money they have.
输入某人的比特币地址，然后立即查看他们有多少钱。
I represent high net worth clients, institutional investors
我代表高净值客户，机构投资者
and for them this kind of feature is a showstopper.
对他们来说，这种功能是风靡一时的。
Nobody with wealth wants anyone in the world to type in
没有人希望别人输入他们的信息就知道他们有多少钱，
their bank account and see instantly how much money they have.
进入他们的银行帐户中，立即看到他们有多少钱。
Or see instantly whenever they transfer money out or get money in
或者，无论他们何时转帐或入款，都可以立即看到
as you can do in the Bitcoin blockchain.
就像您在比特币区块链中所做的一样。
You can set a little automated robot to like,
您可以设置一个自动化的机器人来监控别人，
watch the blockchain for you and send you an alert on your cellphone
监视区块链并在手机上向您发送警报
whenever a transaction goes in and out of any Bitcoin address that you choose.
每当交易进出您选择的任何比特币地址时。
This sort of kind of casual surveillance,
这种监视，
this invitation to be creepy on your neighbor
这种情况，让人感到毛骨悚然
is something that is intrinsically part of Bitcoin.
而这是比特币本质上的一部分。
And the deeper (it) gets into society,
越深入社会，
the more insidious it is,
越危险，
the more of a threat it is to all of our privacy.
对我们所有隐私的威胁就越大。
A slander that happens is that
同时有一种说法，
"okay, so you have this money that doesn't have a history,
“好吧，门罗币是没有历史的钱，
sounds like only the criminals are going to want to use it".
可听起来只有罪犯会想要使用它”。
It is a slander I'm kind of tired of hearing.
这种诽谤，我都听烦了。
Monero benefits people who have nothing to hide.
门罗币当然使光明磊落的人们受益。
The chief benefit is that
门罗的主要好处是
with the money that has no memory,
用没有记忆的钱
there's no need to worry about being falsely accused of misdeeds due
无需担心被错误地指控为不当行为
to being one hop away from a "bad person".
远离“坏人”。
Basically, when you accept a surveillance coin,
基本上，当您接受监控硬币时，
you are accepting the risk that somebody unsavory will be sending you something.
您正在接受某些风险，那就是有些不讨人喜欢的人会向您发送东西。
For example, let's say you have a business you sell stickers or
举例来说，假设您经营一家公司，出售贴纸或
t-shirts or something very innocent
T恤或很正常的商品
and you decide that you're going to accept Bitcoin for your business.
并且您决定要接受比特币作为您的业务。
Unbeknownst to you, you get a t-shirt order from a gangster
不知情的情况下，您从黑帮那里获得了一件T恤订单
or some drug dealer or someone like that.
或一些毒贩或类似的人。
You had no idea they're a drug dealer, they're just sending you some Bitcoin because you're a t-shirt seller
您不知道他们是毒贩，他们只是向您发送一些比特币要买东西，因为您是T恤销售商，你只是卖东西收钱
and this is how you make money
这就是你赚钱的方式，
you need to get money from people.
您需要从人们那里获取金钱。
But because the people watching the blockchain and putting faces and names
但是，其他人通过观察区块链和真实的人之间的关联
on addresses on blockchain, don't know that
单纯通过地址并不知道
they can try to program that in
可他们可以用计算机分析
but in the end, it's a probabilistic assessment of
最后，它很可能认为
is this bad person really related to you.
这个坏人真的和你有关系，因为你跟黑帮，毒贩有资金往来
The only way that somebody finds out that they've been bitten by this is that
收款人大多时候不觉得有事，直到这种侥幸维持的平静被打破
"oh, geez, Coinbase just emailed me and my account's been closed."
“哦，天哪，Coinbase刚给我发了电子邮件，我的帐户已被关闭。”
"Even the Fiat bank that I had associated with my crypto exchange"
“甚至与我的加密货币交易所关联的银行也被关了”
"now thinks that there's something suspicious about me."
“他们认为我有些可疑资金往来。”
"Now my Fiat bank has frozen my funds for some reason" --
“现在我的银行出于某种原因冻结了我的资金”
and it had nothing to do with anything that the person in question did.
受害者与有关罪犯所做的一切无关。
It's just that the money itself has this
只是比特本身有这个
fatal flaw of being totally, (of) having a history behind it.
具有全部历史的致命缺陷。
It's not really money,
它不是真正意义上的货币
it's like beanie babies, it's like collectables.
这就像豆豆公仔（类似于芭比娃娃），就像收藏品。
It's like collectible items with their own serial number that are getting passed around in this economy,
就像具有自己的序列号的可收藏物品在这种经济中正在流传，
it's not a real money.
比特币不是真正意义上的货币。
I want to leave with a Nobel Prize winning idea.
我想引用一个诺贝尔奖获得者的理论。
I find that not too many people have heard of this paper.
我发现没有多少人听说过这篇论文。
George Akerlof won the Nobel Prize in Economics for his work on asymmetric information in markets.
乔治·阿克洛夫（George Akerlof）因其在市场中的非对称信息方面的工作而获得了诺贝尔经济学奖。
Anyone here know this paper well?
这里有人对这篇文章很了解吗？
Okay. Great.
好的，赞。
I'll explain it briefly.
我将简要说明。
There are two kinds of used cars.
有两种二手车。
There are lemons, which are the bad used cars.
一种车我们叫它柠檬，代表坏的二手车。
Those are... you buy them and then they break immediately - those are lemons.
那些是...您购买它们，然后它们立即破裂-那些破车俚语里就叫柠檬。
The other kind of used car is a peach - these are the good cars.
另一种二手车是桃子-桃子代表是好车。
Those owners of the peaches, they did all the maintenance.
那些桃子的主人，他们做了所有的维护工作。
They change the oil, they did all the work to make sure that they have a nice car to sell.
他们更换机油，并做了所有工作以确保有一辆好车要出售。
Sellers know whether they're selling a lemon or a peach.
卖家知道他们在卖柠檬车还是桃子车。
The seller knows that. If you're selling a lemon, you know it.
卖方知道这一点。如果你卖破车，你怎么可能不知道。
And you're just trying to make money off the selling of the lemon.
而且卖家只是想通过卖柠檬破车来赚钱。
If you have a peach, you know it because you've been doing maintenance on that car.
如果你卖桃子车，那你也就知道了，因为您一直在对该车进行保养。
However, the buyer of the car is ignorant
但是，汽车的买主却一无所知
because both lemon sellers and peach sellers make extra sure that the paint job on the car is extra shiny.
因为柠檬销售商和桃子销售商都会确保汽车上的油漆特别有光泽（表面工作）。
The cars all look alike to the buyer
这些车对买家来说都一样
so the buyer knows that they are vulnerable in this situation.
因此买方知道在这种情况下他们很脆弱。
The buyer knows that they could end up with a lemon.
买家知道他们最终可能会得到柠檬。
Because the buyer is ignorant but not totally ignorant.
因为买方是无知的，但不是完全无知的。
They are actually aware of their own ignorance.
他们实际上意识到自己的无知。
(And) because of that, the buyer then adjusts their offer price to be slightly lower than that of a peach.
因此，买方随后将其报价调整为略低于桃子的报价。
The asking, offer price for the car is going to be not quite at the peach price here.
这辆车的要价将不完全符合桃子的价格。
It's going to be slightly lower.
它将略低。
What happens then?
那会发生什么呢？
If you're selling a lemon and you see this pretty high price being offered for cars, you're happy.
如果您在卖柠檬，而看到汽车的价格很高，那您会很高兴。
Because your lemon, which is worth this low price, can sell for this.
因为您的柠檬值得这个低价，因此可以出售。
So the lemon sellers are happy.
所以柠檬卖主很高兴。
There are more suckers out there to buy their lemons.
还会吸引更多人买他们的柠檬破车。
How about the peach sellers? The peach sellers are the ones who did the work to have a good car to sell
桃子卖家呢？卖桃子的人是那些努力卖出好车的人
and now they're seeing this offer price which is less than the peach price.
现在他们看到这个报价比桃子的成本价格还低。
They're discouraged and slightly offended
他们感到灰心和沮丧
because all that work they did, all the good work that they did to keep that car good.
因为他们所做了所有工作，以及为保持车良好所做的所有出色工作。
And they followed all the rules with their car.
他们用汽车遵守所有规则。
That good behavior is not getting rewarded in the form of a high price coming from the buyer.
良好行为并不会以买方高价获得回报。
So the peach sellers get discouraged, they leave the market.
因此，桃子销售商感到灰心，他们离开了市场。
What happens is that peach sellers leave.
发生的事情是桃子卖家离开了。
Well, now the buyers figure out that
好吧，现在买家知道
their chance of buying a lemon has just gone up
他们买柠檬的机会增加了
and the price that they're going to offer goes down.
他们愿意买车所出的价格下降了。（因为更大概率买破车）
And you have this race to the bottom in which the offer price keeps going down, down, down.
而且市场在这种恶性循环里，底价竞价中一直处于下降状态。
All of the good sellers leave the market
所有好的卖家都离开了市场，
because they are not being justly compensated for the work that they've done.
因为他们所做的工作没有得到应有的报酬。
What does it have to do the cryptocurrency?
这个故事对加密货币有什么启发？
Surveillance coins
比特币这种监控币
which have a total record and a total history of who had them
拥有总记录和谁拥有它们的总历史
are the used cars of cryptocurrency.
是加密货币的二手车。
Whenever you buy Bitcoin from somebody and you don't know the history of that Bitcoin,
每当您从某人那里购买比特币时，您都不知道该比特币的历史，
you are the used car buyer in this situation.
您是这种情况下的二手车买家。
You don't know if you accept this Bitcoin...
你不知道你是否接受这个比特币...
"Am I going to be just fine or am I going to be falsely accused of some who knows what?"
“这个币干净吗？还是我会被错误地指控某些犯罪？”（洗钱，毒贩，交易所被盗的币）
Who knows what possible crime could have been done with the person who used to own that Bitcoin.
谁知道与曾经拥有该比特币的人可能犯下的罪行。
You don't know if that's going to happen to you.
您不知道这是否会发生在您身上。
As a Bitcoin receiver, you are in the position of the used car buyer.
作为比特币接收者，您处于二手车购买者的位置。
What in this paper is identified as
这篇文章的结论
a means to avoid this race to the bottom -- is a signal.
用一个均衡的状态避免这种恶行循环。
So in the car market, for example
因此，例如在汽车市场上
and there's probably something similar to this in Europe,
在欧洲可能与此类似，
where you can type in the serial number, the VIN number of a car
您可以在二手车系统中输入序列号，也就是汽车的VIN码（独一无二的该车代码）
and then you get a report...
然后您会得到报告...
you can see if it's been in an accident...
您可以查看是否发生了事故...
this doesn't exist in Europe? Okay, well.
在欧洲不存在吗？好吧
Business idea for somebody...
某人的经营理念...
It exists in the United States. It's called Carfax
它存在于美国。叫做Carfax
and you type in the serial number of a car and all of its kind of past history comes up.
您输入汽车的序列号，就会显示所有过去的历史。（新西兰也有这种系统）
That information can equalize the playing field between the buyers and the sellers of cars.
该信息可以平衡汽车买卖双方之间的竞争环境。
This also happens in the job market.
在就业市场中也会发生这种情况。
Education is a similar situation.
教育也是类似情况。
If you are a boss, you're hiring a worker... you have a hundred workers out there applying for jobs.
如果您是老板，那么您正在雇用一个工人...您那里有一百个工人正在申请工作。
They all look the same to you because it's like
它们在您看来都一样，因为
everyone starts looking the same.
每个人看起来都一样。
All the resumes look the same after a while.
一段时间后，所有简历看起来都一样。
So how are the sellers of their labor going to distinguish themselves?
那么，他们的劳动力如何与众不同？
They're going to have a signal.
他们将发出信号。
Education is a signal just like information in the used car market is.
就像二手车市场中的信息一样，教育也是一种信号。
Basically, the sellers of labor take it upon themselves to get
基本上，劳力的卖方将自己承担
educational credential to signal to the buyer of labor
向劳工购买者发出信号的教育证书
that their labor is going to be worth more.
他们的劳动将变得更有价值。
Unfortunately, what happens is that the sellers of education then figure this out
不幸的是，发生的事情是教育的卖家然后发现了这一点
and then they just start selling education
然后他们才开始出售教育
because they know that the people coming for the education are just going
因为他们知道来接受教育的人会去
to get an employment signal.
得到就业信号。
The actual purpose of the education gets lost.
教育的实际目的迷失了。
This is happening in non-fungible cryptocurrencies as well.
这也在不可互换的加密货币中发生。
Right now, anybody who signs up for an account
现在，任何注册帐户的人
at a centralized exchange
在中央交易所
has to do all sorts of degrading things.
必须做各种有辱人格的事情。
You have to hold up a picture of your ID,
你要拿一张身份证的照片，
you have to make a little handwritten note that says this "this is my name".
您必须做一点手写笔记，写上“这是我的名字”。
You have to basically submit all this stuff just to be deemed worthy enough
您必须基本上提交所有这些东西才被认为足够有价值
to participate in this cryptocurrency economy.
参与这种加密货币交易。
That is a signal in this sense too.
从这个意义上讲，这也是一个信号。
But what's interesting is that in cryptocurrency,
但是有趣的是，在加密货币中，
currently, the exchanges bear the burden of due diligence on their customers.
目前，交易所对客户承担尽职调查的负担。
It's an expense for the exchanges to be doing, to check all these people out.
交易所要检查所有这些人是一项费用。
It could be that in the future that just like in the education market and in the car market.
将来可能就像在教育市场和汽车市场一样。
It's the seller who's going to have to increasingly go through hoops
卖方将不得不越来越困难
basically to prove their worthiness in this whole system.
从根本上证明他们在整个系统中的价值。
Just to take a step back,
现在说回来之前的话题，
I've gone over scarcity in Bitcoin and Monero
我已经阐述了比特币和门罗币的稀缺性
and I've gone over fungibility and privacy in Bitcoin and Monero.
也讨论了比特币和门罗币的可替代性和隐私性。
And if we step back,
如果我们回到一开始的话题，
I can identify what I think is a reason why crypto is not going to go away
我可以很确定，我认为加密技术不会消失的原因
why it's here to stay.
为什么它在世界里长存。
Now we have the internet,
就是现在我们有了互联网，
we have mobile telecommunication
我们有移动通信设备（智能手机）
everybody here has at least one device
这里的每个人至少都有一台电子设备
that is extremely good at copying packets.
它非常擅长复制数据包。
That's what cellphones are. They are just packet copiers.
手机，类似于是小复印机。
When you fetch your email,
当您提取电子邮件时，
you are copying packets from the email server to your phone to check.
您正在将数据包从电子邮件服务器复制到手机以进行检查。
We've become just extraordinarily efficient at copying ones and zeros globally.
在全局复制1和0代码方面，我们已经变得异常高效。
The marginal cost of shuttling these bits around is zero.
将这些位穿梭的边际成本为零。
What is rare in that world,
什么是虚拟世界上稀有的东西
what is rare in a world where every human on earth basically
在这个世界上每个人都需要的稀有东西是什么？
has the ability to copy ones and zeros anywhere around the world for free?
有能力免费在世界任何地方复制1和0？
Well, it's going to be digital scarcity
好吧，这将是数字稀缺
and digital privacy.
和数字隐私。
Digital scarcity in the sense that
数字稀缺性
there's a sequence of ones and zeros that only you know
只有一连串的一和零只有你知道
which is cryptocurrency - that's the private key.
这是加密货币的私钥。
And privacy in which you
还有您的隐私
have a sequence of ones and zeros also you only know
有一个一和零的序列只有你知道
and that you haven't shared with everyone
并且您还没有与所有人共享
like you've shared the contents of your lunch on Facebook with the entire world
就像您已经在整个世界上在Facebook上分享了午餐的内容
and other details of your life that are basically copied around.
和您生活中的其他细节基本上都被复制了。
These are the two things that are going to be scarce in the future:
这是将来将稀缺的两件事：
digital scarcity and digital privacy.
数字稀缺性和数字隐私。
Cryptocurrencies offer both.
加密货币同时提供。
And cryptocurrencies like Monero
还有像Monero这样的加密货币
especially offer both because they offer privacy as well.
尤其要同时提供两者，因为它们也提供了隐私。
So the values of the money we use every day
因此，我们每天使用的金钱价值
are the values fixed by the government.
是他人确定的价值观。
The paper bills and even the coins
纸币甚至硬币
are not in themselves actually worth
本身并不值钱
the amounts they represent.
它们代表的数量。
Their face values, however, are guaranteed --
但是，可以保证他们的面值
not only by huge reserves of gold and silver
不仅是大量的黄金和白银储备，
but by the stability of the government
还由政府的稳定背书
which fixed those values.
他们共同确保了这些价值。
As long as people remain confident
只要人们保持自信
that our government is strong and secure,
我们的政府是强大而安全的，
they will continue freely
法币将继续自由
to accept and spend its money
接受并花钱他们的货币
without questioning the value.
毫无疑问的价值。
In the past when we've had Fiat money,
过去我们有法币的钱时
basically, your nationality
基本上是你的国籍
told you what community you belong to for purposes of money.
告诉您您属于哪个社区以赚钱。
If you're born in the Eurozone, well, you use Euros.
如果您出生在欧元区，那么您会使用欧元
I was born American, so I use the US dollar.
我是美国人，所以我用美元。
That kind of gets told to you at birth
这种在出生时就被告知
as an accident of where you were born.
随机且与生俱来的。
Now with cryptocurrencies,
现在有了加密货币，
because the system of bookkeeping is a decentralized network of computers that can be worldwide
因为系统是分散的计算机网络，可以在全球范围内使用
this idea of association is now fluid.
这种想法现在很不稳定。
It's more open, it's really like the Reformation of the Church.
它更开放，就像是教会的改革。
Another famous German, Martin Luther
另一个著名的德国人马丁·路德
who liberated theology from the kind of
谁从那种神学中解放出来
centralized control of the Catholic Church
天主教的集中控制
and liberated this ability for people to elect
并解放了人们选举的能力
to worship in the way that they chose.
以他们选择的方式崇拜。
A similar sort of thing is now possible, because of Nakamoto consensus,
由于中本聪的共识，现在有可能发生类似的事情，
almost 11 years and a month old.
它提出快11年零一个月了。
Now it's possible for each one of us to kind of pick a group,
现在我们每个人都有可能选择一个小组，
"pick your own church," pick your own...
“选择自己的教堂”，选择自己的...
like, that's not really quite right
就像，这不是很确切的比喻
but I think you get what I'm saying.
但我想你们明白我的意思。
You can pick your own group of people who agree
您可以选择自己认同的人
on certain characteristics that they want their money to have
他们希望自己的钱拥有的某些特征
and you are free to associate with each of those groups.
并且您可以自由地与每个组产生联系。
Bitcoin is one such group that apparently doesn't
比特币显然不是这样的一个群体
really, is not too bothered by the fact that
因为你未来理想的比特币总会被以下事实困扰
the currency has this perfect knowledge of history for every single coin that's out there.
对于存在的每个比特币，该货币都具有可以称得上'完美'的历史记录。
And that is a large association of people all of whom have the shared belief
并且即便这样很多绝大部分比特币成员仍旧认为这是他们的共识
that the token that they are keeping track of on their blockchain is money
既他们在区块链上可以一直被跟踪的代币就是金钱
and there's a similar sort of community,
还有一个类似监视币的社区，
sort of formation that happens with the cryptocurrencies.
某种程度上加密货币发展也会格式化。
I'd like to share some of my observations about the Monero community
我想分享一些有关Monero社区的看法
and by the way, I'm volunteering to be here.
顺便说一句，我自愿来这里发表演讲。
I've paid my own dime to come out here from Boston
我自己付钱从波士顿来这
to kind of share what I think
分享我的想法
my understanding of the current status of cryptocurrencies with you.
与你分享我对加密货币当前状态的理解。
Monero is basically, it's run like a charity.
基本上，门罗币是靠捐助活下来的。
There is no company behind it.
它背后没有公司。
There's no pre-mine, there's no scammy way for people to get rich.
没有预挖，没有人骗其他人而暴富。
All of the Monero in existence were given in the past to a miner
过去所有现存的门罗币都交给了矿工
who was doing the accounting work to help support the network, just like in Bitcoin.
就像在比特币中一样，他正在做会计工作以帮助支持网络。
Both Bitcoin and Monero have the positive aspect that there's
比特币和门罗币都有积极的方面，那就是
no central company steering things to kind of make a profit.
没有中央公司指导事情以牟取暴利。
No, it's totally open-source grassroots.
是的，这是完全开源的草根。
Just normal everyday people choosing to run some
就像普通人每天选择运行
peer-to-peer network software on their computer
他们计算机上的相应网络软件
and join this community who have this shared
并加入这个分享的社区
ethos in what they think that money should be.
构建他们理性中的钱。
The Monero community, I find it to be idealistic scientific and yet very welcoming.
我发现门罗币社区是理想主义的科学，而且非常受欢迎。
It's very chill.
他们很酷.
There's like a lot of alpha geek happening in some other coins,
其他一些社区中也有许多 alpha geek（天才程序员）
in which people are just really out there on Twitter
在推特上，很多很出众的
and they just really want everyone to know that they're the "alpha-est" geek out there.
但他们只是希望每个人都知道他们是那里最天才的计算机程序员
That kind of thing is refreshingly absent in Monero.
在Monero社区里就不是这样。
It's very chill.
他们真的很酷。
It's one thing that kind of I like about this whole vibe here at c3.
我喜欢36c3黑客大会上的整个氛围。
It's very chill, there's just like a lot of people lounging
非常酷，天涯何必曾相识（里面各个都是认才，说话又好听）
and that sort of shared relaxed atmosphere is something that I've
而那种共享轻松的氛围是我曾经也
personally observed at the Monero meetups that I've been to.
在我去过的门罗聚会上亲自感受到的。
Monero Research Lab - we have full-time PhDs
门罗研究院，我们拥有全职博士学位
who do nothing but cryptographic research.
除了密码研究之外什么都不做。
There's sort of a pipeline of research in which
有种各种研究线路
pure science gets done at Monero Research Lab.
纯科学在门罗币研究实验室完成。
Then, implementations of the promising idea get tested out
然后，对有前途的想法的实现进行测试
then there's an audit process that we actually employ
然后我们实际采用了一个审核流程
external auditors to look at implementations of code.
外部审核员来检查代码的实现。
Once those are clean, then we go to release.
一旦校验结束，我们便开始应用。
There's this basically pipeline of technology from science to engineering
从科学到工程，这基本上是一条技术管道
that gets pushed out in the actual release of the Monero
不断发布新版本的门罗
core software.
核心软件。
The LMDB database is another kind of interesting example of how far Monero has come.
LMDB数据库是门罗币走了多远的另一种有趣的示例。
In the early days of Monero,
在门罗币的早期，
the entire blockchain was stored in RAM
整个区块链都存储在RAM中
if you can believe that.
简直不敢让人相信的。
So, that kind of puts a hard limit on how big your blockchain can be
也就是说，当时对门罗用户的区块链空间施加了很大硬性要求
if it has to fit in RAM.
因为当时必须放入RAM。
The LMDB block database - which was the brainchild of Howard Chu
LMDB块数据库-这是Howard Chu（中文社区喜欢管他叫教授）的创意
who is one of the very frequent contributors
他是最频繁的贡献者之一，
and sort of an open-source Linux guru - was added to Monero.
老炮开源Linux专家  -> 已加入Monero。
Monero is actually number three in terms of developer effort
就开发人员的努力而言，门罗币实际上排名第三，
if you look at the... if you rank the coins not by market cap but by actual developer effort.
如果您看……如果您不是根据市值而是根据实际开发人员的努力对硬币进行排名。
It goes Bitcoin, Ethereum and then Monero.
先是比特币，以太坊，然后是门罗币。
It turns out that,
坦率地说，
well, in my opinion,
在我看来，
the killer app of Nakamoto consensus is money
中本聪共识的杀手级应用是金钱，
because you have a ledger of scarcity that's being shared.
因为您有一个正在共享的稀缺账本。
And what's a more natural thing is there for
还有更自然的事情，
a shared idea of scarcity, then money?
共同的稀缺观念，然后是金钱？
But it turns out that money is non-trivial to get right.
但是事实证明，赚钱是不容易的。
It needs to be thought through.
需要深思熟虑。
These things like... should the money have a complete history behind it
诸如...这些钱应该有完整的历史记录吗？
or should it be fungible?
还是应该可互换的？
Like that kind of basic idea that
像这样的基本思想，
basic engineering design decision has to be made early on
基本工程设计决策必须尽早做出，
because the technology that's needed to bake in fungibility to Monero -- it's highly non-trivial.
Monero具有互换性所需的技术-这是非常重要的。
Monero has been added for 6 years now
Monero已经6年了
and has made great improvements in that.
并在此方面做了很大的改进。
And the way that the social contract is,
这也是社区共识进化的方式
I just can't see this happening in Bitcoin.
我只是看不到这种情况在比特币中发生。
There are volunteer workgroups for community outreach
门罗币有志愿工作组开展社区外联活动
and, as I said before,
就像我之前说的
all of the funding to support all of this is completely 100% shaking the tin cup
所有支持这一切的资金完全是100％募捐而来
and asking for people to donate out of the kindness of their hearts.
人们出于自己的善意而捐款。
And the people in the Monero community do that.
Monero社区中的人们做到了。
They actually step up to the plate
他们挺身而出，
and they fulfill these.
他们实现了这些。
But if you look at the annual budget
但是，如果您查看年度预算，
if Monero were a company, which it's not --
假设门罗币是一家公司，当然门罗不是公司
but if Monero were a company and you looked at its operating budget,
但是如果Monero是一家公司，而您查看了其运营预算，
you would be astounded at how minuscule, how tiny it is.
您会惊讶于它的微小，多么微小。
And that's because you have idealistic, passionate people
那是因为你有理想主义，热情的人
working on this project in true open-source spirit,
本着真正的开源精神从事这个项目，
often on their spare time.
经常在业余时间。
All right.
好的。
So, just to summarize,
让我们总结一下，
Monero is what Bitcoin newbs think they bought.
门罗币是比特币新手认为他们购买的东西。
I'm going to switch hats a little bit.
我要稍微多说一点。
As I mentioned, one of my jobs before going full time in crypto
正如我提到的，在从事全职加密工作之前，我的工作之一是
I was head of research at a hedge fund
我曾是一家对冲基金的研究主管
and the question of thinking of cryptocurrency as an investment comes up.
并提出了将加密货币视为一项投资的问题。
And of course because there have been these spectacular gains in the price of Bitcoin,
当然，因为比特币的价格获得了这些惊人的收益，
it gets discussed a lot.
讨论了很多该方案。
One thing that is positive about Monero's culture is that it is generally
对门罗币文化有利的一件事是，它通常是
gauche to talk about prices,
不讨论价格的，
and returns, and the price going to the moon.
门罗社区不讨论回报，价格飞涨。
I hope that, well --
当然我希望如此，好吧。
I have some background in academic finance;
我在学术金融方面有一定背景；
there's a paper that I co-authored on the effect of liquidity on asset prices
我合著了一篇关于流动性对资产价格的影响的论文
that won a "paper of the year" award in applied finance;
获得了应用金融“年度论文”奖；
and that, coupled with the Nobel Prize that I just explained --
再加上我刚才解释的诺贝尔奖-
hopefully, I can put a respectable enough academic sheen on the discussion of
希望我可以在门罗币价值讨论方面给予足够可观的学术知识
the finance and economics to be forgivable by the Monero community.
门罗币社区可能忽略了金融和经济学层面。
But the fact is that this project is going to attract investors,
但事实是，该项目将吸引投资者，
it's going to attract hodlers.
它会吸引锁仓者。
It's a socioeconomic hedge.
这是一种社会经济对冲。
There are lots of investment, there are lots of ETFs out there.
有很多投资，那里有很多ETF。
If you believe that companies should be environmentally sustainable
如果您认为公司应该在环境方面具有可持续性
and that their corporate boards should have official policies that
他们的公司董事会应该有官方政策
mandate sustainability in one sense or another,
在某种意义上要求可持续性，
there are ETFs that will only invest in those companies.
有些ETF只会投资那些公司。
It's possible to be basically an ideological investor
基本上可以称为意识形态投资者
if you really care about sustainability
如果您真的关心可持续性
and there's an investment for you.
这就是您的投资。
If, for example, like say Islamic finance --
例如，如果说伊斯兰金融-
they are not cool with the idea of interest being paid on loans,
他们对借贷支付利息的想法不满意，
so you have another subset of Islamic finance investments
所以你有另一套伊斯兰金融投资
that don't involve paying interest on loans.
不涉及支付贷款利息。
Monero - if you look at it in a similar lens - is basically an ideal hedge 门罗（Monero）
如果以相似的角度观察-基本上是理想的避险工具
for people who have two characteristics.
对于具有两个特征的人。
One is that they're concerned about mismanagement and corruption
一是他们担心管理不善和腐败
on the part of central banks managing Fiat
在管理法币的中央银行方面
and two, they're gravely disturbed by the state of surveillance capitalism
第二，他们受到监视资本主义状况的严重困扰
in which everything about all of us is recorded all the time
记录着我们所有人的所有时间
and will stay forever,
并将永远存在，
and we have little or no control over that.
我们对此几乎没有控制。
It's done in the name of security
以安全的名义监视
but unfortunately, if you push that line too far,
但是如果这条路走的太远，
you cease to become an open and free society.
我们将不再成为一个开放和自由的社会。
There are reasons that we, in the West, have put limits on the powers of government
在西方，我们有理由限制政府的权力
and that is because of an awareness of what happens when there are no limits on the powers of government.
这是因为人们意识到当政府权力不受限制时会发生什么。
A project like Monero is a hedge
像Monero这样的项目是对冲
it's basically a "put your money where your mouth is" kind of thing
这基本上是一种“把钱放在嘴里”的事情
for people who have strong feelings on those two points
对于对这两点有强烈感情的人
it's just going to attract investors.
它只会吸引投资者。
Gresham's law is an economic concept that the best form of money gets hoarded.
格雷沙姆定律是一种经济概念，最佳货币形式。
People keep the best kind of money
人们保留最好的钱
and the inferior form of money, they're going to use that to spend.
以及劣等的金钱形式，他们将用它来花费。
But the good stuff, they're going to keep for themselves. That's Gresham's law.
但是好东西，他们会自己保留。那是格雷舍姆定律。
So with Monero, this tends to happen.
因此，对于门罗币，这往往会发生。
A lot of people in Monero used to be in Bitcoin,
Monero中有很多人曾经使用比特币，
but now, whenever they deal with Bitcoin,
但是现在，只要他们交易比特币，
they find their heads consumed with all these worries about traceability
他们发现自己对所有关于可追溯性的担忧
and so on.
还有其它的担忧。
It's refreshing to come to Monero
但来到Monero世界之后令人耳目一新
where you don't have to worry about that
在这里你不必担心
because the currency is actually fungible.
因为货币实际上是可互换的。
And because it's fungible, it becomes a superior form of money
而且由于它是可互换的，因此成为一种优越的货币形式
that gets hoarded by Gresham's law.
遵循格雷沙姆的法法则。
That's another tendency that's going to happen to people: to want to keep the Monero
这是人们将会发生的另一种趋势：想保留门罗币
and spend the other stuff.
并花掉其他东西。
Also, capital gains taxes:
另外，资本利得税：
at least in America, and I believe in Germany too,
至少在美国，我也相信在德国，
if you hold an asset for over a year in Germany, you don't have to pay gains on it.
如果您在德国持有资产超过一年，则不必为此付出收益。
That's what I've read. Is that right in Germany? (nods)
这就是我读过的。在德国，对吗？ （点头）
Basically, the tax law
税法根本上就会
promotes looking at those cryptocurrency projects that are solid
促进那些扎实的加密货币项目
and have a real reason to exist
并让加密货币有真实的理由存在
and so that is also going to attract investment money to Monero.
因此这也将吸引投资资金到Monero。
The question is: can these new investors integrate into the community?
问题是：这些新投资者可以融入社区吗？
Part of what I do as a consultant is I try to bridge these worlds.
作为顾问，我要做的部分工作就是尝试弥合这些世界。
I try to take these new investors
我试图吸引这些新投资者
whose inclination might be to want to talk to the "manager of Monero"
其倾向可能是想与“门罗币的经理”交谈
and have a word with them about the release schedule.
并与他们谈谈发布时间表。
And they want this, and this and this feature
他们想要这个，这个和这个功能
built into the next release
内置于下一个版本中
basically, this whole mentality of
基本上，他们的心态就是
"I own some tokens therefore I'm your customer and you have to do what I say"
“我拥有一些代币，因此我是您的客户，您必须按我说的做”
which of course falls completely flat on its face in any open-source project
当然，在任何开源项目中，那些人都会失望
as that's not how changes happen in Linux.
因为这不是Linux中更改发生的方式。
Nobody goes to Linux and demands,
没有人去寻求Linux系统的要求，
makes ultimatums on what they want to see in the next rollout.
对他们希望在下一次发布中看到的内容进行最后通.。
Basically, one thing that I'm doing is
基本上，我正在做的一件事是
trying to bridge these worlds of the traditional investment world
试图弥合传统投资世界和新世界
and that of the OG, cryptocurrency open-source world
以及OG（加密货币开源世界）
that's surrounding us here.
在我们周围。
Community investors,
社区投资者
I posit are kind of a subset of investors that
我认为有些投资者
can be valued members of the community. Instead of being
可以成为社区的重要成员。而不是
entitled and thinking that they're customers,
有权并认为他们是客户，
they'll take the attitude that they're helping to bear financial risk
他们会以帮助承担财务风险的态度
on behalf of the project.
代表该项目。
They will do things like take self-custody of their coins
他们会做一些事情，例如自己保管自己的币
and not just leave them on exchange - which lots of people do.
而不仅仅是让他们把币放交易所-很多人都这样做。
Lots of people leave their crypto on exchanges
很多人在交易所留下他们的加密货币
then the exchange gets hacked, they lose their money.
然后交易所被黑客入侵，他们失去了钱。
The reality is: if the money is on the exchange,
现实是：如果钱在交易所，
you don't own the private key and it's not your crypto.
您不拥有私钥，也不是您的加密货币。
It's actually an IOU that you own for crypto,
实际上，您拥有加密货币的借条，
it's not crypto that you own
您拥有的不是加密货币
and there's a kind of a list of aspects that I think are proper for
我认为有一些方面适合
a community type of investor to be a solid member of the Monero community.
一个社区类型的投资者，成为Monero社区的坚实成员。
One thing to do, also, is to make sure that
同样，要做的一件事是确保
there are proper legal structures around one's ownership of cryptocurrency.
围绕一个人的加密货币所有权有适当的法律结构。
One of the subsets of the traditional finance world that I help to bridge with cryptocurrencies is that of trusts.
我帮助与加密货币建立联系的传统金融世界的子集之一是信任。
In a statutory law kind of regime like Germany,
在像德国这样的成文法制下，
the whole concept of trust might be a little foreign
整个信任的概念可能有点陌生
because it comes from English common law.
因为它来自英国普通法。
But the idea is that a trust is a legal entity,
但想法是，信托是法人实体，
it's a legal thing.
这是合法的事情。
It's kind of a company
这是一家公司
but it's a different category of legal structure.
但这是法律结构的另一类。
A trust is a
信任是一种
kind of a holding vessel for funds that
是一种存放资金的船只
a giver wants to give to beneficiaries but not immediately.
捐献者希望立即捐献给受益人。
Basically, there are three people involved.
基本上有三个人参与。
There's a grantor who has wealth and wants to transfer it to the beneficiaries
有一个拥有者的财富，想将其转移给受益人
but not just outright, they want the money to go into a trust.
但他们不只是要彻底，还希望这笔钱能用于信托。
The grantor will work to make the rules of the trust
设保人将努力制定信托规则
and then transfer property into the trust
然后将财产转移到信托中
as part of the document that defines the trust,
作为定义信任的文档的一部分，
you have a list of beneficiaries who could ultimately benefit from the property
您有最终受益人的财产清单
and then you have a third party which is the trustee.
然后您有一个第三方，即受托人。
The trustee is the legal owner of the assets that are given into trust
受托人是信托资产的合法所有者
but the legal owner is with conditions.
但法定所有人有条件。
The legal owner cannot do whatever they want with the property,
法定所有人无法对财产做任何想做的事情，
they have to follow the instructions that are in the trust document.
他们必须遵循信任文档中的说明。
In effect, this is what crypto people would think of as a smart contract.
实际上，这就是加密人们认为的智能合约。
It's kind of the original old-school legal contract
这是原始的旧式法律合同
and if you're careful with
如果您对
which jurisdictions you place the various players in the trust,
您将各个参与者置于哪个司法管辖区，
there are advantages that can be had --
有很多优点-
which are very dependent on jurisdiction,
非常依赖司法管辖权
and it's just completely impossible for me to spell it out
对我来说，完全不可能讲清楚
because of the complexity of this --
由于这很复杂-
but possible benefits are legal tax reduction,
但可能的好处是合法减税，
protection from being sued.
保护免受起诉。
In other words, if money is in a trust,
换句话说，如果钱是信托的，
it's not the giver's money anymore,
不再是施主的钱了
it's not the wealth owner's money anymore, it's the trus't money.
它不再是财富所有者的钱，而不再是桁架的钱。
If somebody sues the wealth owner, the wealth is gone.
如果有人起诉财富所有者，那么财富就不复存在了。
It's not theirs anymore, it belongs the trust.
不再是他们的了，它属于信任。
And then there are trust laws that protect that money from lawsuits as well.
然后，还有信托法也保护这笔钱不受诉讼。
Most people think "well, you know, I'm at low risk.
大多数人认为“好吧，我的风险很低。
I'm a nice guy I don't hurt anybody, nobody's going to sue me".
我是一个好人，我不会伤害任何人，没有人会起诉我。”
But one glaring exception to this is divorce.
但是离婚的一个明显例外是离婚。
People routinely get robbed by people who they only recently married
人们通常会被刚结婚的人抢劫
and it turns out that irrevocable trusts made before marriage --
事实证明，婚前不可撤销的信任-
you have to do it before or otherwise it won't count --
您必须先执行此操作，否则它将不起作用-
but it's one of the only things that can survive a challenge.
但这是唯一可以经受住挑战的事物之一。
Also, legal enhanced privacy
此外，法律增强了隐私
so depending on the jurisdiction in which you place the trust,
因此，根据您放置信托的司法管辖区，
you could benefit from enhanced privacy protecting those assets.
您可以从保护这些资产的增强的隐私权中受益。
Actually, relevant to people who are not Americans,
实际上，与不是美国人的人有关，
you may or may not be aware of this,
您可能知道，也可能不知道，
but there's a saying within estate planning and wealth management
但是在房地产规划和财富管理领域有一种说法
that "America is the new Switzerland."
“美国是新的瑞士”。
And this is because America has laws that are asymmetric.
这是因为美国的法律不对称。
America has a law called FATCA, which was put in by Obama,
美国有一项称为FATCA的法律，该法律是由奥巴马制定的，
which requires worldwide financial institutions to send data on Americans back to the IRS.
这要求全球金融机构将有关美国人的数据发送回国税局。
This is why it's almost impossible for an American to get a German bank account
这就是为什么美国人几乎不可能获得德国银行帐户的原因
because the German bank account
因为德国的银行帐户
will have a whole bunch of burdensome reporting requirements
将有很多繁琐的报告要求
to the IRS to take on this American customer.
向美国国税局（IRS）征集该美国客户。
That's why Americans have a lot of trouble
这就是为什么美国人有很多麻烦
when they go overseas to work.
他们出国工作时。
In reaction to this, the other countries of the world came up with what's called CRS
为此，世界其他国家提出了CRS
which is the "Common Reporting Standard."
这就是“通用报告标准”。
The idea is the same, for example:
想法是相同的，例如：
one European government wants to make sure that
一个欧洲政府希望确保
its citizens are not trying to hide money in Australia,
它的公民没有试图在澳大利亚藏钱，
so they sign this like agreement
所以他们像协议一样签字
for all these countries to share financial information with each other
让所有这些国家彼此共享财务信息
to make sure that nobody's cheating on their taxes.
确保没有人欺骗他们的税收。
There's basically a bunch of countries that have signed on to this CRS
基本上有很多国家已经签署了此CRS
but America is not one of them.
但是美国不是其中之一。
Thus lies the asymmetry
因此存在不对称
that for US citizens who doing affairs abroad,
对于在国外做事的美国公民来说，
like legitimate businesses abroad,
像国外的合法企业一样
all of that information gets sent back to the IRS.
所有这些信息都被发送回国税局。
But for a non-US person who sets up financial affairs in the US,
但是对于在美国从事金融事务的非美国籍人士，
there is no obligation for the US to send the information back to the home country.
美国没有义务将信息发送回本国。
So, thus the saying, "America is the new Switzerland."
因此，俗话说“美国是新的瑞士”。
The two small dippers vibrate on the surface of the water.
两个小号北斗在水表面振动。
Each dipper produces its own pulse
每个北斗会产生自己的脉冲
and the two sets of patterns overlap.
并且两组模式重叠。
Now the dippers are put out of step.
现在，将铲斗放到不合时宜的位置。
They are vibrating in anti-phase
它们反相振动
and produce a different pattern.
并产生不同的模式
In step, they produce a pattern like this.
在步骤中，他们产生了这样的模式。
Out of step, the pattern is like this.
步调不一致，模式是这样的。
This is kind of a complicated one but
这有点复杂，但是
this is showing the degree to which the monthly ups and downs of Monero
这显示了门罗币每月起伏的程度
versus the monthly ups and downs of Bitcoin
与比特币的每月起伏
versus the monthly ups and downs of the US stock market,
相对于美国股市的每月涨跌，
the US bond market and gold.
美国债券市场和黄金。
For example, this square here
例如，这里的这个
is showing the intersection of Monero and Bitcoin.
显示了门罗币和比特币的交集。
On this axis you see the Monero return,
在此轴上，您可以看到门罗币反弹，
on this axis you see the Bitcoin return.
在这个轴上，您会看到比特币的回报。
You can see that on months when Monero does well,
您可以看到在Monero表现良好的几个月中，
Bitcoin also tends to do well.
比特币也表现良好。
You have this kind of pattern, this correlation.
您有这种模式，这种关联。
Here you can also see that there's some really extreme outlier months for Monero in the positive though.
在这里，您还可以看到，门罗币有一些非常极端的异常月份。
This particular month, Monero basically quadrupled in one month.
在这个特定月份，门罗币基本上在一个月内翻了两番。
This is part of owning crypto --
这是拥有加密货币的一部分-
that you're on this really wild rollercoaster ride --
您正处于这种疯狂的过山车之旅中-
and you need to kind of be able to deal with that.
并且您需要能够处理这种情况。
But what this is showing is that
但是，这表明
there is a correlation between the returns of Monero and Bitcoin.
门罗币和比特币的回报之间存在相关性。
That's a .4 correlation.
那是.4的相关性。
A 1.00 correlation is perfectly correlated.
1.00 相关系数是完全相关的。
They go up and down together.
他们一起上下。
Negative 1 is the opposite. If one goes up, the other goes down.
负1相反。如果一个上升，另一个下降。
In Modern Portfolio Theory --
在现代投资组合理论中-
and this is true for also your own personal portfolio, it's an idea to think about --
这对于您自己的个人投资组合也是正确的，这是一个思考的想法-
if you have two assets who you expect to do well in the future
如果您有两项资产，希望将来会做得更好
and they're uncorrelated, in other words,
它们是不相关的，换句话说，
when one asset goes up the other is flat or maybe the other one goes down,
当一项资产上升而另一项资产持平或另一项下降时，
in other words, the ups and downs from day to day of these two different assets
换句话说，这两种不同资产的日常起伏
tend to cancel each other out.
倾向于互相抵消。
If you have that situation
如果你有这种情况
then if you make a portfolio out of both of those assets
然后，如果您同时使用这两种资产制作投资组合
your combined volatility is going to be improved.
您的综合波动率将得到改善。
It's going to be reduced
它会减少
because the components that you're adding are anti-correlated.
因为您要添加的组件是反相关的。
This is a very big deal for Wall Street investors
对于华尔街投资者而言，这是一笔非常大的交易
because it turns out correlation structure tends to be more dependable and long-lived
因为事实证明相关结构趋向于更可靠且寿命更长
than predictions of outperformance, so
比预期的好，所以
correlation structures tend to persist.
相关结构倾向于持续存在。
Wall Street is always looking for sources of uncorrelated alpha.
华尔街一直在寻找不相关阿尔法的来源。
For example, if you look at the correlation of Monero with traditional assets like US stocks, we have 0,01.
例如，如果您查看门罗币与美国资产等传统资产的相关性，则为0,01。
An idea to think about is that
要考虑的一个想法是
putting together assets that wiggle in different ways can be
将以不同方式摆动的资产放在一起
a positive force for your overall portfolio.
为您的整体投资组合带来积极影响。
Now again, as I mentioned, this is only talking about correlation structure.
再次，正如我提到的，这只是在谈论相关结构。
This is like the ups and downs. This is not talking about
这就像跌宕起伏。这不是在谈论
"is the price going to go up in the future."
“未来价格会上涨吗？”
That's a different question.
那是一个不同的问题。
Let me show this and then I'll finish.
让我展示一下，然后结束演讲。
I'm sorry, I'm going over -- but I guess there's no one after me --
抱歉，我快讲完了-但我想我后面没有其他发言人了-
but I'll try to make it quick.
但我会尽力加快速度。
I think what I'm showing here is pretty much the only asset price chart you need
我认为我在这里显示的几乎是您所需的唯一资产价格图表
and that is a very long term view.
这是一个非常长期的看法。
This is showing from the beginning of cryptocurrency, 2009 to 2020.
从加密货币的开始（2009年至2020年）就可以看出这一点。
This is 11 years of history
这是11年的历史
and you almost never see this in the crypto bloggers
而且您几乎从未在加密博客中看到这一点
or people on YouTube blabbing about crypto.
或YouTube上热衷于加密的人们。
They're always focused on what happened yesterday.
他们总是专注于昨天发生的事情。
It's totally a distraction
完全分心
for anyone who has a long term view.
对于任何有长期看法的人。
So, I would suggest whenever looking at crypto as an asset, to zoom out on the horizontal scale
因此，我建议每当将加密货币视为资产时，都应缩小水平范围
and also zoom out on the vertical scale.
并缩小垂直比例。
What I'm showing here: each of these [y axis] divisions is a factor of 10.
我在这里显示的是：[y轴]除法中的每一个都是10的因数。
Here we have 1 cent, 1 dollar and 10 thousand dollars.
在这里，我们有1美分，1美元和1万美元。
This is an initial investment of one euro becoming 10 million euros, that's the scale.
这是一欧元的初期投资，即一千万欧元，即规模。
And on this sort of scale,
在这种规模上
all of these ups and downs
所有这些跌宕起伏
which seem big, disappear.
看起来很大，消失了。
For example, let's look at the S&P 500,
例如，让我们看一下标准普尔500
the US stock market.
美国股市。
If you're involved at all in the stock market,
如果您完全涉足股票市场，
you know that December 2019 has been a very good month.
您知道2019年12月是非常好的月份。
We're talking 15% up
我们正在谈论15％的增长
which is really big for the stock market.
这对股市真的很大。
But if you look on this scale, it's like a pixel.
但是，如果以这种比例看，它就像一个像素。
I think this underlines the decision
我认为这突出了决定
that anyone has when thinking about cryptocurrency as a possible investment.
任何人在将加密货币视为一种可能的投资时都会想到的。
It's this baby. It's still a baby.
它还是个孩子
It's amazing because it's gone up orders of magnitude
虽然很神奇了，因为它上升了几个数量级
and yet compared to other assets, it's still a baby.
可与其他资产相比，它仍然是婴儿。
This next chart shows that.
下一张图表显示了这一点。
What I've done here is --
我在这里所做的是-
it's hard to understand if somebody tells you that the price of Bitcoin is $7,000.
如果有人告诉您比特币的价格是7,000美元，就很难理解。
It's hard to know whether that's high or low. Who knows?
很难知道这是高还是低。谁知道？
It's just really hard to know
真的很难知道
because it's just one Bitcoin
因为那只是一个比特币
and it's hard to put that in perspective.
而且很难将其视为正确的观点。
What I've done here is I've taken the
我在这里所做的是
value of all of the Bitcoin in existence.
存在的所有比特币的价值。
Starting from the beginning of Bitcoin, as time goes on,
从比特币的开始，随着时间的流逝，
more Bitcoins got rewarded to miners
矿工获得了更多的比特币奖励
so there have been more Bitcoins in existence
所以有更多的比特币存在
and the price has been going up and down.
价格一直在上涨和下跌。
I multiplied the number of Bitcoins in existence by the current price
我将现有比特币的数量乘以当前价格
and that gives you the market cap.
这给了你市值。
What I've done with that is I've divided that
我所做的就是我将其分开
by the value of all of the gold, above ground, in the world.
取决于世界上所有黄金的价值。
All of the gold that has been already been dug out of the ground
所有已经被挖出的黄金
and is sitting in vaults around the world
并坐在世界各地的保险库中
and owned mostly by central governments,
并主要归中央政府所有，
but also a good amount is in jewelry, and so on,
但是珠宝中也有很多，依此类推，
and there are estimates of this.
并且对此有估计。
Basically, there are estimates for how much gold there is in the world at any given time
基本上，可以估算出在任何给定时间世界上有多少黄金
so I've divided the value of all the world's Bitcoin
所以我将全球所有比特币的价值进行了划分
divided by the value of all the world's gold.
除以世界上所有黄金的价值。
And I've done that for 11 years.
我已经做了11年了。
What you can see here is that,
您可以在这里看到的是，
currently, the value of all the Bitcoin in the world is about 1% of that of all the gold.
目前，世界上所有比特币的价值约为所有黄金的1％。
In other words, all the gold is worth a hundred times what all the Bitcoin is worth.
换句话说，所有黄金的价值是所有比特币价值的一百倍。
And if you do that for Monero --
如果您为Monero这样做-
and, arguably, this analogy is even more apt for Monero,
可以说，这个比喻更适合门罗币，
because when you turn a bar of gold over,
因为当你把一块金条翻过来时，
you don't see a list of everyone who owned that bar of gold,
您不会看到拥有该金条的所有人的列表，
you just see gold --
你只看到黄金-
Monero acts more like actual gold than Bitcoin does,
门罗币的行为比比特币更像实际的黄金，
therefore, it makes more sense to make a ratio of all the world's Monero,
因此，更合理地设定全世界所有门罗币的比例，
how much is that worth --
那值多少钱-
divided by how much all the world's gold is worth
除以世界上所有黄金的价值
if you do that, we're looking at 1/100 of 1%.
如果您这样做，我们将查看1％的1/100。
That's what I mean when I say that this asset class is still a baby, it's still early.
这就是我说这个资产类别仍然是婴儿时，还很早的意思。
Things could go well for it, things could go very wrong for it.
事情可能会顺利进行，事情可能会出错。
There could be a bug that nobody knows about.
可能存在一个没人知道的错误。
There could be governmental action which a lot of people
可能会有很多人采取的政府行动
I think overly worry about
我觉得太担心了
because I think we geeks tend to think of governments as being like Reddit moderators
因为我认为我们的天才们倾向于认为政府就像Reddit主持人一样
with ban power.
具有禁令的权力。
And that's not really how governments work,
这并不是政府的运作方式，
it's a bit more deliberative --
这是经过深思熟虑的-
and if an unjust ban happens, there are things like the Supreme Court
如果发生不公正的禁令，诸如最高法院
that might be asked to decide whether, for example,
可能会被要求决定是否例如
Americans have a fundamental right to transact value in a private manner.
美国人享有私下交易价值的基本权利。
This could be a court case that comes up in the future
这可能是将来要提起的诉讼
put forth by people
人们提出的
who really care about privacy as a fundamental human right.
谁真正关心隐私是一项基本人权。
I'll leave with that, and thanks for your attention.
我将离开，并感谢您的关注。